Hi, welcome back to Nagarjuna.
I made a mistake at the
end of the last class.
I said we're finished with
the chapter, but we're not.
We're still in the same chapter.
I think it's chapter 16,
which is talking about
being chained to sansara
and then getting nirvana,
which is releasing the chains
and getting away from sansara.
This second half of this chapter
doesn't take very long to teach.
So I thought you guys might
like to see something,
you could appreciate,
the work of trying to
translate these texts,
trying to find these texts.
So you're kind of at the
end of the food chain.
You are speaking of chains.
You are getting all this information,
all these teachings
because of other people,
who worked so hard to find
the books, catalog the books,
scan the books, input the
books, save the books.
And I'm talking about ALL,
all of the hard work they do.
So my part is the easy part,
I just explain something.
I get the book because other
people have worked so hard
for over 30 years to find these books
and to bring me books.
They're like these guys
that go out in the world,
find the books and they
bring them back home.
I get to sit and read them
and share them with you.
So I kind of wanted to
recognize that huge effort
of John Brady and his whole team of ALL,
also all the Gold Clubs,
the "club de oros" around the world,
all of you guys who are
working so hard to raise money.
I think sometimes, if I'm you,
I would think well what
do they do with the money?
Where's the money go?
And I thought you would appreciate
seeing how your donation
became this class.
So first of all,
the donations made 20, 22 years ago,
they went into, we were trying to find
Choney Lama's books. And
they were, you know...
In those days, it was
very hard to get a copy
of any of Choney Lama's books.
My teacher showed me
one book of Choney Lama
and I was like, wow!
I studied, he has 250 books like this.
Come on, Rinpoche, give them to me.
He's like, "No, you can't get them."
And I was like, "What do
you mean we can't get them?"
He says, "We made a mistake."
And I'm like "Who's we?"
He says, "My monastery,
Sera Me, we made a mistake."
I'm like, "Well, what's the mistake?"
He says, "We didn't want other monasteries
to get Choney Lama's books because then
we could win all the debates
with the other monasteries.
So we kept all of the Choney
Lama's books very carefully."
I'm like, "Well, what happened?"
He said, "Well, we kept
them in the library."
I'm like, "What happened to the library?"
He says, "Well, during
the cultural revolution
the library was bombed
and it all burned up."
Every copy burned up.
We made a booboo. We put
all the copies in one place
nobody else... probably
that's the karma, right?
Nobody else could get them.
Then they all burned up.
Then we ran away.
That's why I'm teaching you right now.
I'm like, so we started
looking for Choney Lama's,
any copies of Choney Lama's books
and finally Jason Dunbar,
who was a great ALL,
early worker for ALL, he went to Tibet
and he went to Choney
monastery and he begged
for scans of Choney Lama's
books and he got them.
And he got all of them, and
I'd like to show you one here.
And, you know, in those days,
copy machines in east
Tibet, Choney district,
they weren't too good,
but you can see it's
a pretty cool carving.
And that's what it looks like.
The end paper, the sideways
letters on the left side,
they say @RTZA...
which means RTZA BA SHES RAB KYI @TI KA
RTZA BA SHES RAB KYI TI KA
TI KA means commentary,
and RTZA BA SHES RAB
is root text on Wisdom.
So you find the name of
the book is at the end,
and then the page number is there which is
@... BDUN, sorry,
yeah, @...TRUS DUN which means 67.
And then there'll be a volume
number, which is probably LNGA.
And that means his collected
works are multiple volumes.
So if the page gets
separated from the book,
which often happens because
they're not bound together,
then you can find the
book and put it back in.
Because teachers are always
giving pages to their students
and say memorize that, give
me back the page tomorrow,
and they never do.
And so there's the copy
from Choney monastery,
and it was the only
copy that we could find.
And so anytime we had a question
we didn't have any place to check.
We didn't have anything to compare it to,
there was no other
carving available to us.
And it often happens
that you have a question
about a carving. Is the
carving correct or not?
So then we ended up going to Russia.
We found, I don't know,
141,000 Tibetan manuscripts
in the collection of the king.
The Czar of Russia had a
collection that he collected,
he was a book collector.
Russians are inveterate book
collectors, they love books,
and he collected 141,000 manuscripts.
And we found a second copy.
So here's a, you can
see in the next picture,
this is a copy of Choney Lama's work.
Much better carving, as you
can see, and more clear.
It took 12 years
to catalog those books.
It took 12 years not to
copy them, not to scan them,
it took 12 years to write the names down.
And we had three guys working full-time.
And then once we saw,
in the contract, we had something
in the contract that said
we can make copies of
our monastery's books,
and we got permission to make copies.
Let me see that copy again.
Now, if the guy holding the paper down
while the roller is going
across the ink on the woodblock
looks up at some, probably
not a girl, but something,
and then he'll get these
big stripes down the page,
you see on the right side,
there's a blank spot?
And then, you know,
Geshe-la has to try to guess
what was there on the woodblock,
and it's really, really
difficult sometimes.
So it's very important to
have multiple woodblocks.
It's very, very important
to go around the world
and try to find another copy.
And it takes money to fly
from East Tibet to Russia.
It takes money to talk
Russians into letting you
work on their books for 12 years,
and that's what you guys
are fundraising for.
It takes a lot of money.
It has, I would say 5 to
10 million dollars so far,
and we're about 5% finished.
So, you know, if we want
to have these classes
and if we want to be
released from the chains
that bind us to sansara,
whoever it is that is bound to sansara,
we need these books,
and then we need money.
It costs money to fly around
and go into ancient libraries
and spend months and months, years,
12 years, it takes money.
Those guys who lived in St. Petersburg...
St. Petersburg is the most
expensive European city
because you can't grow anything there.
When I went there they said
don't spend much money on dinner.
And so I said okay.
And so I went to dinner, I
said all I want is a salad.
And they gave me a salad and
the next day I said okay,
I didn't spend much money on dinner.
- What'd you buy?
- I bought a salad.
- Oh my God, that's the
most expensive thing!
You know, that's like $50.
I'm like why?
They said, "You're in
Russia, it's too cold,
you can't grow vegetables here, duh!
You should've had some sheep
meat or something [laughs].
So it costs money to stay
there, it costs money to,
a lot of money to stay there for 12 years.
And also all kinds of problems.
We got, one of our staff got kidnapped
by the mafia in Russia.
They said 50,000 bucks or
we're going to kill him,
and you know, that's expensive.
So anyway, one more
thing I want to show you
of why John Brady is so brilliant
and why his project
deserves your help so much,
let's see the next slide.
Now this is the woodblock
from Choney monastery.
Probably it was printed
sometime around 1700,
I mean carved around 1700.
And if you know Tibetan,
look at the fourth line, okay Tim?
You want to read it slowly?
From GZHAN.
Come on!
RGYU DANG 'BRAS BU
NYID DANG
Keep going.
DANG NI
MTSAN GZHI
NYID DANG
Okay, good.
It says 'BRAS BU NYID
DANG NI MTSAN GZHI NYID
And Geshe-la is translating,
Geshe-la's preparing for this class.
And Geshe-la's going crazy
because it doesn't make sense.
There's something wrong here.
Like Geshe-la, after many, many years,
you smell something's missing.
Like there's something's missing here.
And by the way, Tim,
you can appreciate it.
He's got pairs here, he's
got members of pairs.
He's got RGYU and 'BRAS
BU, cause and effect.
Later he's going to have
TSOR BA and TSOR BA PO,
the feeling and the feeler.
And then between that you've got
thing defined with no definition.
You've got thing defined,
it's a list of pairs,
but there's one single guy in the middle.
It should have, what word is missing?
This is what is defined,
we need the word for?
Definition, MTSAN NYID.
MTSAN NYID is missing here.
So Geshe-la spends three hours,
he struggles, struggle,
struggle, struggle,
and then he says the goddamn block,
there's something wrong with the block.
That guy was also looking up at something
and didn't carve definition.
In the block, you know?
So what does Geshe-la do?
Yeah, I got to go find the other block,
but if ALL hasn't had the money
to fly to St. Petersburg
and stay there for 12 years,
I won't have a second block, got it?
That's why we need the Gold Club,
and that's why you guys have
to support the Gold Club.
Even $5, even $1, if there's enough mice,
they can hold up the Titanic.
[students laughing]
That's the whole story
with the gold clubs.
We're not, it's not big, rich people,
it's a bunch of small
people who give $1, $5, $10,
and then we hold up the Titanic.
So I want to play with you.
Geshe-la decided there's
something missing from the block,
Geshe-la went to the second
block, let's go see it.
By the way, I did this
in the car this morning.
Now, Tim, read the third line.
MTSAN NYID DANG MTSAN GZHI NYID
Yeah, what's there?
The word that Geshe-la
predicted should be there.
There's definition, MTSAN
NYID and MTSAN GZHI.
Go back, go back, make it big.
Now, $100.
How the hell did they
change the woodblock?
Somebody corrected it like 200 years ago.
Somebody sat there like
Geshe-la for three hours
and said something's wrong here,
and then they corrected it.
But how do you correct a woodblock?
You shave off the letters
and you dig up a square spot,
then you take a piece of wood
and make it the same size
and you glue it into the
block and then you recarve it.
But there's no room to recarve it
because we're adding a
word, so what do you do?
You shrink everything!
Look at the third line, it's very cool.
You shrink everything.
He's trying, the guy's
trying to carve, you know...
- Hey, could you just
fit in two more words?
- What?
- Come on, you can do it.
And you can see this guy
sitting there carving.
It would take about, I don't know,
three or four hours to carve it.
And he's carving everything smaller,
so if you look at the
picture you can see that.
It's very cool to me,
some guy took the block,
cut out the missing part, and glued it in.
And that's why it's smaller, got it, cool?
Isn't that cool?
Now, if Gold Club doesn't send guys
to St. Petersburg library,
then I cannot explain the book to you
because there's something
wrong with the book, got it?
And then it's wrong forever.
If we don't fix it, trust me,
no one else cares about it [laughs].
All right?
So I think it's cool.
All right, now let's go
to the impossible book.
The book's already impossible,
but if there's words missing,
it gets a little more difficult [laughs].
All right, here we go.
,GAL TE NYE BAR LEN 'CHING NA,
,NYE BAR LEN BCAS 'CHING MI 'GYUR,
,NYE BAR LEN MED MI 'CHING STE,
,GNAS SKABS GANG ZHIG 'CHING BAR 'GYUR,
Don't forget we're talking
about being chained.
'CHING BA means "chained", right?
Chained, who's chained
to what, by the way?
We are chained to what?
[student responding indistinctly]
Mind and body which are, oops, messed up.
Okay, we're chained to a
messed up body and mind.
We are chained to a mortal body
and we are chained to an f-ed up mind.
Okay? [laughs] That's the chains, got it?
- Who's chained?
- Michael.
Okay, Michael is chained to
a messed up body and mind.
Okay.
- Is Michael the chain?
- No, I mean, you chain somebody
to a wall in a dungeon, right?
You chain a prisoner to the wall.
Is the chain part of the wall,
or is the chain part of the prisoner?
- Neither, I mean it's between
the prisoner and the wall, right?
Got it?
So, and by the way, in the Abhidharma,
the chain is a separate entity.
It's very interesting.
They say there's your body and
mind and then there's Pachi,
and the chain is some kind
of mystical third thing
that keeps Pachi chained
to his body and mind.
And Nagarjuna's like come on, you know.
Either the chain is part
of the body and mind,
or the chain is part of the guy
who's chained to the body and mind.
But the chain, where else
is the chain going to be?
The guy dies, what happens,
the chain just sits around
and the whole universe
is filled with chains?
You know?
Who's getting chained?
Who's chained?
And then, I'm going to
skip to this last line.
SONG DANG MA SONG BGOM PAS BSTAN
$100, BGOM, $100.
Yeah, he's correct, it's not meditation.
[student speaking indistinctly]
No, nothing to do with meditation.
We learned it like 100 times, but.
[student speaking indistinctly]
Very similar spelling and
exactly the same pronunciation
because it has a prefix.
For $50 I'll give you a clue.
[students laughing]
It came before.
It came in the second chapter, $25.
Walking, yay, 25 bucks for Gyelse, yay!
Awesome.
All right, oh you cheated, okay.
That's all right, don't tell me.
Yeah, walking.
What's that got to do with chains?
$100.
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, wait, he's showing me.
Yeah, here.
Where's the...
[students responding indistinctly]
Yeah, where's the part?
There's a part of the path
that you walked, there's
a part of the path you
haven't walked yet.
The part of the path
that you're walking on
is supposed to be somewhere between,
but you can't define it,
and that's very similar
to the idea of the chains.
The middle point, the part of the path
that you're stepping on now, BGOM.
because BGOM is always active.
Stepping, it's not really walking
it's putting your foot down.
Where's the part of your path,
where is the exact part of the
path of the present moment?
[vocalizing]
Where is the present moment?
That's where the chain is.
Got it? It's cool, right?
Where is the chain?
Oh, it's like halfway between
you and your body and mind.
[laughs]
So Nagarjuna's like get it?
Halfway between you
and your body and mind.
So let's do the language here.
GAL TE NYE BAR LEN 'CHING NA
If you are chained to your body and mind,
NYE BAR LEN BCAS 'CHING MI 'GYUR,
then you're not chained.
If the chain is part of your body and mind
then the chain's not part of you.
How's that?
NYE BAR LEN MED MI 'CHING STE
Then, if you let go of your body and mind,
you wouldn't be chained anymore.
If you died you wouldn't
be chained anymore,
you'd go to Nirvana.
If the chain is part of your
messed up body and mind,
then when you drop a body
and mind, as you keep doing,
then you should be unchained for awhile.
GNAS SKABS GANG ZHIG 'CHING BAR 'GYUR
Then what point is it
where you're chained?
Now, same argument, you
tell me where it comes from.
For $100, god you guys are
making so much money today.
Ready?
Everybody's like...
Did the chains exist
before the guy was chained?
Now, what's the $100, Geshe-la?
You take me back to a previous verse
in this series of classes.
[student responding indistinctly]
That's good, but we were
talking before that.
By the way, the ninth chapter's name
is "Was There Something There Before".
The ninth chapter's
name is an investigation
of whether something was there before.
And it referred to one of the senses.
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, when you look at something...
Yeah, is the eye there?
Is the little girl with
the telescope there?
She walks outside and
then the stars are there?
Does the perceiver come first
or the seeing comes first?
Which one?
Does the little girl walk
out with the telescope
and then looks at the
stars, or how does it work?
Does the little girl with the telescope
walk out of her house and
then look at the stars?
[student responding indistinctly]
She has to, she has to because
there has to be a telescope
before there's astronomy.
But she can't because
she's not an astronomer
till she looks at the stars.
So the whole thing's impossible.
Now take that here.
Chains, did the chains come first,
or the chain-ee came first?
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, good, you can't be a chain-ee
until you've been chained.
But you've got to have
chains to be chained first.
Okay, the whole thing
is something messed up.
And the point is,
if there's trouble in the kitchen
figuring out why the husband's upset,
you have to look for other options.
Maybe it's all coming from you.
Okay, that's the bottom line.
Maybe you make the telescope
and then you make the girl
and you make the astronomy.
All coming from you.
But they are not causing
each other, out there.
[vocalizing]
It looks like [vocalizing],
but it's really [vocalizing].
Okay, got it?
That's all.
If you realize it's [vocalizing],
then you can do Medicine Buddha mantra.
But if you think you're
[vocalizing], you're in trouble.
If you're out there doing
Medicine Buddha mantras,
you're in trouble.
If you realize that the
mantra comes from you,
the illness comes from you,
the fixing comes from you,
then you can use a mantra, cool?
Yay, let's go to the next one.
Oh, by the way, next picture.
Is the guy shackled or not?
Wait, no, the guy before that.
[laughs]
Is this guy shackled?
No, because there's no chains yet.
Therefore the chains have
to come first, right?
Nevermind.
Next verse.
RE ZHIG BCINGS PA
MI GROL TE,
MA BCINGS PA YANG GROL MI 'GYUR,
Okay.
This is very subtle.
It says...
RE ZHIG means provisionally,
for the time being, for now.
RE ZHIG -- for now.
BCINGS PA MI GROL TE
You cannot take off your chains.
Let's look, it's kind of like look.
Look, you can't take off your chains. Why?
First of all, he's like
that, first of all,
Nagarjuna, first of all, you
cannot take off your chains,
you cannot take off these chains.
You cannot not fight with your husband.
You cannot take off these chains. Why?
Because you see the chains.
You cannot take off the chains. Why?
Because you think those
chains are coming this way.
Then you, the way you think
about the chains is the chain.
Got it?
You can't, he just says, "Hey
let me tell you something."
- What?
- You can't take these chains off.
- Why?
- Because these chains
are coming this way.
And thinking they're coming
this way is the real chains.
It's very sexy.
Thinking the chains are coming this way
when you look at the
chains is the real chain,
and if you look at the chains
then you're going to be
chained more and more.
You guys, okay, got it?
Very sexy.
MA BCINGS PA YANG GROL MI 'GYUR
Even if I took the chains off you,
you would still be chained [laughs].
Okay, got it?
BCINGS PA GROL BZHIN YIN 'GYUR NA
BCINGS DANG GROL BA DUS GCIG 'GYUR
If there was a middle
point in the stepping
of the foot on the path,
between being chained and unchained,
then in the same, then somewhere,
the part of the path where you have been
and the part of the path where
you will be have to touch.
If there's a place between
chained and unchained that can touch,
then you can be chained and
unchained in the same moment.
It's not possible.
Like you can see Nagarjuna going...
Okay, we can make a dance, right?
Some kind of Hawaiian thing.
Okay, next verse.
,BDAG NI LEN MED MYA NGAN 'DA',
,MYANG 'DAS BDAG GIR 'GYUR RO ZHES,
Let's just start with the first two lines,
because this gets heavy,
this gets difficult.
BDAG NI LEN MED MYA NGAN 'DA'
If I could not @NYE BAR LEN PA,
but that would be MYA NGAN LAS 'DAS PA.
If I could stop @NYE BAR LEN PA-ing,
I could reach Nirvana.
What's @NYE BAR LEN PA?
[student responding indistinctly]
Yeah, if I could stop taking
on new bodies and minds,
that's Nirvana, you know?
If I could stop taking
on cancer filled bodies
and anger filled minds,
that would be Nirvana,
you know, if I could stop that.
MYANG 'DAS BDAG GIR 'GYUR RO ZHES
I would like to make Nirvana my own.
BDAG 'GYUR
Then you're already in trouble,
because me, my, me and my.
That's the definition
of the misunderstanding
which is which link of the wheel of life?
[student responding indistinctly]
The blind man, which link?
Number one, causes everything else.
The minute you say I want Nirvana,
then you're already in trouble.
Who's me? Who's I?
What Nirvana?
BDAG GIR ZHES means
I want to make it mine.
But, Christina, the word for mine in...
the word for me "atman"
also means
[student responding indistinctly]
self nature, self nature.
When we say BDAG MED, "anatman", anatman,
no self nature.
The word for "me" in Tibetan and Sanskrit
is the word for self existence.
So when Nagarjuna says,
hey, what do you want to do?
- I want to reach Nirvana.
- What do you want to do to Nirvana?
- I want to make it mine.
Oh yeah, self existing mine, yeah, cool.
Got it?
Atman.
I want the atman to own the Nirvana.
But atman don't exist
because atman means self nature.
All right, DE LTAR GANG DAG 'DZIN DE YI.
NYER LEN 'DZIN PA CHEN PO YIN
Your desire to make Nirvana your own
is just an advanced form
of misunderstanding.
Whoa.
Your desire to make Nirvana my own
is link number one in the
goddamn wheel of life!
Duh, okay!
- I want to get out of the wheel of life.
- Yeah, okay, how?
- I'm going to make Nirvana my own.
- Yeah, cool, that's the first
link in the wheel of life.
[laughs] Got it?
You should be laughing, I
don't know what's going on.
Let's do it again.
- I want to get out of the wheel of life.
- Yeah, really? What are you going to do?
- I'm going to make Nirvana my own.
Oh yeah, that's the first
link in the wheel of life,
very good, very good [laughs].
Okay, got it?
It's kind of funny.
GANG LA MYA NGAN 'DAS BSKYED MED
'KHOR BA BSAL BA'ANG YOD MIN PA
This is very difficult
and you need Choney Lama.
The line says
nowhere could you create Nirvana.
Nowhere could you BSKYED. This
is the D, BSKYED with the D
which means "to create"
as opposed to "be born".
Without the D -- "be born",
with the D -- "create".
What's the most famous use of this verb?
That's pretty close.
That's actually true.
How about SEMS BSKYED?
To give birth to the mind,
to give birth to the
wish for enlightenment.
So, but here, okay, $100 question.
God, you guys are making
so much money today.
Choney Lama says... the word BSKYED
here, which means to create,
"You want to create your Nirvana, right?"
You want to bring, you want
to create your Nirvana.
He says the word create
here is a code word
for SGRO 'DOGS
in that pair called SGRO
'DOGS and SKUR 'DEBS.
- [Jigme] Overestimation.
- Yay, $100!
Jigme, can you pay Jigme $100?
Now which Jigme takes the money
and which Jigme gives the money?
And where's the line between?
Yeah, overrate.
So what's it mean here?
When you say I want to make Nirvana mine,
you are creating a fake Nirvana.
You are creating a self existent Nirvana.
When you say I want to make Nirvana mine,
you are creating Nirvana.
And then Choney Lama says,
"When Nagarjuna says create here,
he means a self existent Nirvana, got it?
Okay, 'KHOR BA BSAL BA'ANG YOD MIN PA.
'KHOR BA BSAL BA means
you couldn't also remove that Nirvana.
BSAL BA here,
which before meant "ajate",
for $100?
- [Woman] Drive.
- Damn, $100!
To drive.
Before, BSAL BA
meant "to drive", right,
the existence of a thing.
Here it means BSAL BA
like clear light BSAL BA.
To remove.
If you try to make a Nirvana
yours which is self existent,
that would be also a Nirvana
that would always be the same
and could never be real.
DE LA 'KHOR BA CI ZHIG YIN
What do you think Nirvana is?
That's, who's asking?
CI ZHIG
I'm sorry, you guys who
are creating a Nirvana,
what do you think sansara is?
What do you think?
What do you think Sansara is?
Now, you want to know
some frustrating thing?
The answer is missing from both carvings.
[students laughing]
It's amazing.
Nobody noticed it for 370 years.
Okay?
I don't know what's going on.
I don't know what they're
doing in those monasteries.
But it's in the Tengyur,
it's in Nagarjuna.
The line exists in the
carving of Nagarjuna
because he's quoting the verse here,
so I went and found it there.
Thank God for club de oro,
so I can go find it in
another, from India,
I found it from India.
And the line was missing,
the whole line was missing.
The answer to the question,
what'd you think sansara was anyway?
And then the answer was
wrong, the answer was missing,
so here's the answer.
MYA NGAN 'DAS PA'ANG CI ZHIG BRTAG
Here's BRTAG.
Yeah, okay.
MYA NGAN 'DAS PA'ANG CI ZHIG BRTAG
What the hell did you
come up with in your mind
when you were wondering
what the hell was Sansara?
CI ZHIG BRTAG
What did you come up
with when I asked you?
We're talking about Nirvana, right,
which is freedom from sansara,
but when I ask you what
the heck is sansara,
you start wandering around BRTAG,
a dumb parīkṣā (pariksha).
You went the wrong way in
your examination, got it?
You did a "estúpido" pariksha.
Pariksha estúpido [laughs].
You did a dumb pariksha.
Okay, got it, you guys?
That's the missing line.
Now maybe it was impolite and
he didn't want to have it.
Let's look at the picture here.
If you can explain the picture to me.
It's a roulette wheel.
What's the point?
In your pursuit of Nirvana...
[student responding indistinctly]
In your pursuit of Nirvana, you are?
You're spinning the wheel again [[aughs].
The way you pursue Nirvana,
spins sansara again.
Yeah, cool, good job [laughs].
You're in pursuit of a Nirvana
for me spins sansara again.
Congratulations, you know?
Your pursuit of Nirvana
is spinning sansara again.
That's the point here.
And I would say, I
don't want to scare you,
but doing Medicine Buddha
mantras the wrong way
would make you sick.
Could sustain the suffering of your body.
Okay, I'm not saying you get cancer
from doing Medicine Buddha
mantras, I'm not saying that.
But what I am saying is
it's possible to do them
in a misunderstood way,
which would sustain illness.
It would spin Sansara rather
than stopping the wheel.
That's heavy, that's heavy.
We have to understand that
to make the mantras work,
we already have to protect
life, or the mantra won't work
and you will die while
you're doing mantras, got it?
Okay, it's a good time,
yay, depressed time to go...
Yes, question?
- [Jigme] That would mean that it's better
not to do any mantras at
all, which [indistinct]-
- It's a good question.
- Yeah, Geshe-la, does that mean
I should stop doing mantras if
I don't understand emptiness.
- No, you should keep doing mantras.
- Why?
- Because when you do
mantras you have, generally,
you have a foundational sweet intent,
and that foundational sweet intent
will help you understand emptiness later.
So if you don't understand
how the mantra works,
keep doing the mantra,
because it can help you
understand how the mantra works,
but don't go too slow to
because you will die first.
Really, seriously, no joke.
But yeah, anytime you do a
mantra, it's a good seed,
maybe for a future life,
if you don't work on
emptiness at the same time.
So do your mantras for half an hour,
go read Nagarjuna for 10 minutes,
come back to your
mantras for half an hour.
That's a good balance.
But don't ignore Nagarjuna and say
I'm going to sit all day and do mantras
because it's very possible you will die
before you get the
benefit from the mantras
or you help anybody.
So keep sprinkling in
the sugar of Nagarjuna,
and don't say it's too hard for me
because sansara is hard and
you got to figure it out.
Okay, all right, get to know Sanskrit.
Yay, let's talk about sansara, sansara.
Hey, you got that?
Yeah, the pronunciation is saṃsāra.
What's that note at the bottom?
Please don't pronounce this as saṃsāra.
That's a mistake about
the M with a dot under it.
M with a dot under it, is not M.
They just didn't have
any other letter to use.
I'm sorry.
So please, it's not M,
it's M with a dot under it.
M with a dot under it means
like those French guys,
like @(speaking in foreign language),
because they talk like this all the time.
Geshe-la you must come to Paris,
you will have the best,
you know, it's that nasal.
So the M with a dot under
it just means [vocalizing].
Sansara, sansara, don't say saMsara.
It happened in, I don't know,
British made this mistake
and it got stuck.
Everybody starts saying samsara, samsara.
Sounds like a guys' name, right?
Hey, meet my friend Sam Sara.
Okay.
And it's especially irritating to me.
By the way, recently
somebody put out a video
with my picture in it and the
Sanskrit was all misspelled.
Please don't do that.
It makes me crazy.
So if you're going to use
my name and my picture,
please, please, please,
please let me check it first.
And somebody else had Tibetan
and it was all misspelled,
in the same time.
So please, please, you
know, because I feel,
maybe you can see I feel
passionate about it.
Okay, so Sri Lanka is misspelled,
Sivananda Yoga Centers is misspelled
because they dropped the diacritic,
they dropped the pronunciation sign
in the same way that the
dot got dropped from the M.
So here's this poor Mr. Sivananda,
whose name is mispronounced forever.
And this poor country whose
name is mispronounced forever.
It's Shri Lanka, it's not Sri Lanka.
But the dot got dropped off.
Okay, got it?
Same thing with samsara.
Okay, Geshe-la, if you
want to irritate Geshe la,
you know how.
Okay, "sam" means to be
together, along with.
By the way, by itself it's "sam",
and then √sṛ means to flow,
and European is √ser also,
and it's found in "serum",
which is a flowing stuff,
and "strudel", which is
interesting, comes from √ser,
because of the whirlpool
look of a good cinnamon roll.
Okay, and doesn't that make sense
for the Sanskrit of sansara?
So strudel and sansara
are inextricably combined.
If you ever have a strudel, give it to me,
and I can take care of it
because that's sansara, same root.
That finishes, let's review what happened.
We were trying to find who is it
that's going to get to Nirvana,
and who is it that is chained
to their body and mind.
And you guys got to think about it.
Everyone says I want to get to Nirvana,
everybody says I want to
escape the wheel of life.
Did you notice the houses
in the wheel of life?
Did you notice the two guys in the boat
Who's the two guys in the
boat in the wheel of life?
[student responding indistinctly]
MING GZUGS
[students responding indistinctly]
Yeah, body and mind, it's body and mind.
When you get out of the wheel,
you're going to have to
leave behind the boat
with the body and mind in it.
Well then who's left [laughs]?
Are you going to go around
without a body and mind?
- Here, meet my friend.
- I can't see him.
- Yeah, sorry, he don't got a body.
- Well, what does he think
about Democrats and Republicans?
- Well, he doesn't think,
he doesn't have a mind.
He left that behind in the wheel of life.
- Well, where is he?
- I don't know.
- You got to think about it.
You keep saying you want to
go to Nirvana, what's that?
I want to dump this body,
which is going to get cancer
sooner or later, okay,
no matter what you drink.
And I want to get rid of this mind
which is all messed up with
jealousy, et cetera, et cetera.
- Okay, what happens
after you get rid of it?
- Oh, I didn't think about that [laughs].
[coughs] I want to get off this bus.
- Then you're standing out
in the middle of the desert.
- You say you want to get off the bus?
- Yeah, but I didn't, I wasn't
thinking what would be left over.
All right, you got to think about it.
Okay, see you in the next class, yay.